Good morning everybody. Today's דף daf is פ"ד, peh dalet, 84. New
פרק, perek, כיסוי הדם. Kisuy Hadam. Actually, because we didn't read it
yesterday, we did not finish the דף daf from before, so we
start right after the משנה Mishnah on the גמרא Gemara on פ"ג
עמוד ב'. peh gimmel amud bet. The משנה Mishnah had said, like
the beginning משנה Mishnah of אותו ואת בנו Oto Ve'et Beno and
like the beginning משנה Mishnah that we're going to see in other
פרקים, prakim, it listed the scope of the מצוה mitzvah of כיסוי
הדם. Kisuy Hadam. It was only applied to חיה chayah and עוף
oph as the verse says, if a person catches חיה chayah and
עוף. oph. Although the תורה Torah talks about capturing, the משנה Mishnah
made a point of saying that animals even that are raised and
not captured... and the other interesting exception was that it does not
apply to sacrifices. You cannot have sacrifices of a חיה, chayah, but
you can of an עוף, oph, and it does not apply in
that case, and of course it would be a little bizarre because
then you would have to throw the dirt on the מזבח Mizbe'ach
because that's where the blood of those birds are going. Another point
just to make is which was raised, which is of course it
shouldn't apply to sacrifices because they're not slaughtered, by the bird you
do מליקה, melikah, but תוספות Tosafot already points out and the גמרא
Gemara will point out that the verse by כיסוי הדם Kisuy Hadam
does not say if you slaughter, it says ושפך את דמו, ve-shaphach
et damo, if you spill the blood. So therefore the idea that
sacrifices were not slaughtered certainly was not the issue per se about
sacrifices. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so
again the גמרא Gemara on פ"ג עמוד ב'. peh gimmel amud bet.
Yes, I wasn't here yesterday, could you just talk about כיסוי הדם,
Kisuy Hadam, what exactly...
Well, we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, but for now let's just
say you slaughter, the blood pools on the ground, you take like
loose dirt, not clumps of dirt, but like sand type of dirt,
loose dirt and you spread it on top so that it is
covered. So that there's a layer of dirt on top. We're going
to see in the גמרא Gemara that what you would not have
expected but we will be saying, which will be causing a whole
discussion initially, is that there needs to be a loose layer of
dirt underneath as well. Okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא
Gemara will get to... the משנה Mishnah did not describe the actual
process, that will come up. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
מוקדשין מאי טעמא לא? Mukdashin mai ta'ama lo? Why does כיסוי הדם
Kisuy Hadam not apply to sacrifices? Again, bird sacrifices because you don't
have it by חיה. chayah. So, אילימא משום דרבי זירא, Ilei-ma mishum
de-Rabbi Zeira, because of רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, and here you go
Rifka, immediately addressing your question about process or about you know the
exact way in which it's done. דאמר רבי זירא, De-amar Rabbi Zeira,
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says, השוחט צריך שיתן עפר למטה ועפר למעלה.
Hashocheit tzarich she-yitein aphar lematah ve-aphar lemalah. The שוחט shocheit has to
put עפר... aphar... has to put dirt but more like dust type
in loose dirt below and loose dirt above. Where do you get
loose dirt below? It says you cover it with dirt. So, שנאמר,
Shene'emar, because the verse says, ושפך את דמו, ve-shaphach et damo, you
spill the blood, וכסהו בעפר, ve-khisso be-aphar, cover it with dirt. עפר
לא נאמר, Aphar lo ne'emar, it doesn't say cover you know have
dirt cover it, אלא בעפר. Ela be-aphar. Now the ב' bet normally
can mean 'with' but it could also mean 'in'. So he's choosing
to read the ב' bet rather than 'with dirt' but 'in dirt'.
So if it's 'in', it means that there's dirt below and dirt
above. מלמד שהשוחט צריך שיתן עפר למטה ועפר למעלה, Melamed she-hashocheit tzarich
she-yitein aphar lematah ve-aphar lemalah, you have to do below, you have
to do above. Because of this teaching, you know and it's interesting
it's just רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, it's not like everybody says it.
You remember that sort of bizarre case the גמרא Gemara had a
while ago where the person hunted was hunting birds and he shot
them with arrows and he made the arrow you know very sharp,
the edge of the arrow, so it שחט shechted the bird in
mid-flight. So the question the גמרא Gemara had is well how did
you do כיסוי הדם? Kisuy Hadam? Even if you went over to
it afterwards, right you have to have loose dirt below. So it
said well you had laid loose dirt all around the valley in
which you were doing your hunting. So anyway, תוספות Tosafot basically does
point out an interesting point that even with רבי זירא's Rabbi Zeira
דרשה, drashah, he's not claiming that the act of כיסוי הדם Kisuy
Hadam is the laying of dirt below. He says that you need
to have there be a layer of dirt below but the act
is still the covering of dirt above. The difference being that you
don't have to do the physical act of laying the loose dirt.
If you basically are doing your slaughtering of your חיה chayah or
your עוף, oph, and there happens to be loose dirt there, but
if it's hard ground that's not the whole point, the whole point
is loose dirt, but if there happens to be loose dirt there
that's fine. Your act, the מצוה mitzvah act, is the putting of
a layer above. But what רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira is saying is
that there needs to be a loose layer of loose dirt present
below.
But can you actually shake the ground so it's loose?
Yes, that would be enough, right, that would presumably be enough.
What about a stone floor?
A stone floor according to רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira would not be
enough. You'd have to spread loose dirt.
In other words, it
is required, but again the תוספות... Tosafot... yes, it's required that there
be loose dirt below but not that there be you do an
act of spreading it. Meaning the act of the מצוה mitzvah is
the placing on top but it requires that it be בעפר be-aphar
that there be a layer of loose dirt present below.
But none of this affects the validity of the שחיטה. shechitah. In
other words you could do שחיטה shechitah without כיסוי הדם.
Kisuy Hadam. That is correct. If no... if you didn't do כיסוי
הדם, Kisuy Hadam, the שחיטה shechitah is totally kosher. Like אותו ואת
בנו. Oto Ve'et Beno. This is just the lack of doing a
מצוה. mitzvah. אותו ואת בנו Oto Ve'et Beno you could actually have
a great violation but it does not invalidate the כשרות kashrut of
the meat. That is correct. Okay, so now why does this explain
why it would not apply to sacrifices? So let's take a look.
The blood of the birds is going on the מזבח. mizbeach. So
you would have to first of all put a layer of dirt
on the מזבח. mizbeach. And right, pack it on also. How loose
could it be if it's held on the wall? Well, that's also
a problem. Right, how loose could it be? Anyway, the גמרא gemara
says היכי ליעבד. heichi le'avid. How do you think you can do
this? ליתיב ולבטליה. leiseiv u'levatlei. Put the layer of dirt on the
altar and sort of annul it there, say that it's there to
remain. כמוסיף בנין. kemosif binyan. You're adding to the structure. וכתיב u'kesiv
it says by the בית המקדש beis hamikdash הכל בכתב מיד השם
עלי השכיל. hakol bichtav miyad hashem alai hiskil.
Everything has been revealed to me, you know, from from the writing
of God as it were. So there was direct instructions what the
בית המקדש beis hamikdash should look like. So you can't now reconstruct,
you know, change the structure of it by expanding the width of
the מזבח mizbeach by adding a layer of dirt. Now תוספות tosfos
actually is a little bit questions this because there's other cases where
it sounds like in the second בית המקדש beis hamikdash they did
change the dimensions of the מזבח. mizbeach. So תוספות tosfos says well,
he quotes רבינו תם rabbeinu tam says maybe it means that you
can't change it from being a perfect square. And if you add
a layer of dirt to get the blood, you'll change it from
being a perfect square. But תוספות tosfos says well then why not
just add a layer of dirt on all sides so that it,
you know, so that you change it proportionally. So anyway he has
different opinions whether it means it can't be changed at all or
it can't be changed from the proportions, but nevertheless you can't add
the layer of dirt and keep it there, that would effectively change
the structure of the מזבח. mizbeach.
Yes, so that's like my question. I mean,
does it mean that it's permanently there? You can't move it? Do
כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam and then take the whole thing and toss
it?
So that's the next question. The next question is so the first
question is if you plan on leaving it there you're changing the
structure. So the next question is so don't plan on leaving it
there. So let's take a look. לא לבטליה. lo livatlei. Just have
a layer of dirt on the מזבח mizbeach again not exactly clear
how you keep it there and keep it loose, but anyway, not
and don't plan to leave it there. And then the blood will
hit that layer of dirt. כהוי חציצה. kehavi chatzitza. So then that
layer of dirt is a separation between the blood and the altar.
If you make the dirt into the altar, the altar wall, so
then it hit the altar wall, but then you've changed the altar.
If you keep it as a layer that's not the altar wall,
then it's a separation. So you cannot do כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam
on the blood that's going to hit the מזבח mizbeach with this
idea of רבי זירא rebbi zeira that there has to be a
layer below as well, not just a layer above.
But it's only חציצה chatzitza if it's not necessary for the מצוה.
mitzvah. I mean, can't you make that argument?
That's an interesting point. Well, I mean, there are questions about when
is something a חציצה chatzitza or not, but this isn't necessary for
the מצוה mitzvah of having it hit the מזבח. mizbeach. This is
necessary for a different מצוה mitzvah of כיסוי הדם. kisuy hadam. True
so. Yeah, okay. But exactly when we sort of say that certain
things that are doing a sort of positive function are or are
not a חציצה chatzitza is I think debatable. But you're right, in
theory I suppose the גמרא gemara could have raised that question. Yes.
In the תורה torah we're taught that we can't add or subtract
anything. Right. Anything. Anything. Right. So the מזבח mizbeach is so holy
how can we...
Well that's basically the point. So you can't add to it. And
even if you just want it there temporarily. Well temporarily isn't adding.
I mean just sort of having, I don't know, if we say
let's say you're going to go wash the מזבח mizbeach we'd say
well you can't add soap and water to it? I mean, you
know, you're just keeping it there for a minute until you get
the blood on it and then you're going to remove it. That's
not really adding. Okay that's at least the גמרא's gemara assumption. Anyway,
the גמרא gemara says, the גמרא gemara isn't convinced that that's sufficient
to explain this. Why? Because the גמרא gemara says the following. נהי
דלמטה לא אפשר. nehi delmata lo efshar.
So okay, maybe you can't have the layer of dirt below which
was all coming from רבי זירא. rebbi zeira. למעלה אפשר. lemala efshar.
So to have כיסוי kisuy
at least you can do the top layer. And why will that
suffice? Because מי לא תניא. mi lo tanya. Did we not teach
in a ברייתא beraisa רבי יונתן בן יוסף אומר. rebbi yonasan ben
yosef omer. שחט חיה ואחר כך שחט בהמה. shachat chaya ve'achar kach
shachat behema. Remember
you only cover the blood of a חיה. chaya. So let's say
first you slaughtered a deer then you slaughtered a cow and the
cow blood fell on top of the deer blood. פטור מלכסות. patur
milichasos. You are exempt, I'm not, same as exempt or sort of
like you've lost the opportunity to cover. Right? Because now you have
all of this cow blood on top of the deer blood there's
no way the deer blood's already covered. You know if you put
a layer of dirt above that's not, you could say well I'm
applying a layer of dirt above it's above both. But the idea
is that the layer of dirt has to effect its covering and
now it is already hidden and covered and buried in the layer
of cow blood. So therefore you cannot do כיסוי kisuy in that
case. Now what if it was the reverse? בהמה ואחר כך חיה.
behema ve'achar kach chaya.
You slaughtered a cow and then you did a deer. So the
deer blood is on the top layer. חייב לכסות. chayav lachasos. So
cover the deer blood. And why are you able to cover the
deer blood? Isn't there cow blood underneath? And didn't we just teach
in the name of רבי זירא rebbi zeira that there has to
be dirt underneath? So you see that even this requirement of רבי
זירא rebbi zeira the גמרא gemara says seems to be that it's
just לכתחילה. lechatchila. That if you don't have the dirt below you
would still fulfill your obligation because here you have the cow blood
below and you still fulfill your obligation. So the גמרא gemara says
no, it's not that you could just dismiss this requirement. כדרבי זירא.
kidrebbi zeira. This is still based on another teaching of רבי זירא.
rebbi zeira. That from רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira, *Rebbe Zeira*, famous teaching
of רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira *Rebbe Zeira*, כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה
מעכבת בו וכל שאינו ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו *Kol hara'uy l'bila
ein bila m'akeves bo, v'chol she'eino ra'uy l'bila bila m'akeves bo*. That
something that can, you in theory could have done it and you
did it, then it's not so bad. But if you in theory
couldn't have done it, now he's got a problem. So this was
said by בילה *bila*, בילה *bila* means the mixing, which is that
you have to be able when you take a, when you make
a מנחה *mincha*, remember way back to מנחות *Menachos*? If you said
you're going to bring a lot of flour, 60 flour, huge amount
of flour,
and you were going to bring it all as one מנחה *mincha*,
so in theory you could mix it with the requisite amount of
oil. What? עשרונים *esronim*, sorry, עשרונים *esronim*.
In theory you could mix it with the requisite amount of oil.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that if you're going to bring
61, you cannot do a reasonable mixing. It's just too large, this
is before they had industrial machines, you cannot reasonably mix it with
the requisite amount of oil. It also might be that the oil
doesn't change in proportion to the flour, then you can certainly understand
once it gets to a certain size why you can't mix it.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says well who cares if you
can't mix it? We know that בדיעבד *b'di'eved* if you don't mix
a מנחה *mincha* it's כשר kosher *kosher*, even if you didn't really
mix the oil and the flour, they were just sort of in
the same כלי *kli*. So it says nope, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira.
*Rebbe Zeira* says that if it can in theory be mixed, then
if you didn't mix it you're still okay. But something that can't
even in theory be mixed is not appropriate, does not count. Okay,
and this becomes the point that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, but
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* of course always wants to know how do you
know whether something is required in practice or just in theory? Okay,
but sometimes we demand that something actually be done, sometimes we do
this middle stage that רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira *Rebbe Zeira* teaches us
that there's a middle stage where you don't require it be done
in practice but it has to have the potential of being done.
And therefore the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that is why by the
way that's just to give a common example that might be a
little more relevant, why when somebody goes to the מקווה *mikvah* they
have to remove a חציצה *chatzitza*, let's say they have something between
their teeth. Now when you go to the מקווה *mikvah* you don't
have to open up your mouth and let the water go in
and do a טבילה *tevilah* inside your mouth, but it has to
be fit and it could be in theory the water has to
be able to cover that inside space. Or if there's a חציצה
*chatzitza* inside of your mouth, it's not a good טבילה *tevilah* because
in theory it couldn't. And so you need it to be able
in theory to be able to do it, not in practice. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that's what's going on here. That
when we say that if you have the cow blood below you
fulfilled your obligation, it's not because you don't need there to be
dirt below. You need it to be at least theoretically possible. So
before you שחט shacht *shachted* the חיה chaya *chaya*, you could have
walked it over a few steps and שחט shachted *shachted* it in
a place where there was dirt below. You happened to do it
in the way that didn't work. At least in theory it could
have been done. But if you're going to שחט shachted *shacht* a
bird sacrifice, we've just demonstrated that there is no way you could
get the dirt below it because there's no way you could add
the dirt layer to the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeach*. And therefore since it's
theoretically impossible, it will never be good. So that's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s argument right now why you do not do כיסוי הדם Kisoy
Hadam, *kisuy hadam* by a bird sacrifice. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says like this. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says I still don't
buy it. ולגרריה ולכסייה *V'ligrerei u'l'chasyiei*. Who says you have to do
the כיסוי Kisoy. *kisuy* exactly in the place where the blood hit?
Maybe you should be able to scrape the blood off of the
altar and then do כיסוי kisuy, *kisuy*. Then move that blood to
a place where there's dirt below, put it on that place, and
then put the dirt above it. Who says it has to be
in situ, in situ or whatever. הלא תניא *Halo tanya*, do we
not teach in a משנה mishna *mishnah*, דם הניתז *dam hanitaz*, if
blood sort of splattered away from the let's say the hole that
you were collecting the blood, the space you were collecting blood, או
שעל הסכין *o she'al hasakin*, or if it's on a knife, how
do you do כיסוי הדם Kisoy Hadam, *kisuy hadam* of the blood
on the knife? What do you do? חייב chayav לכסות *Chayav l'chasos*,
you have to cover it.
אלמא *Alma*, now again this is only a question because of רבי
זירא Rebbi Zeira, *Rebbe Zeira*, because the question is if you just
say cover it, fine, cover it, take dirt and cover it wherever
it is. But רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira, *Rebbe Zeira* remember requires there
be dirt below. So we have to re-read what you're doing here
in order to get the dirt below. How do you get dirt
below if it's on the knife? So אלמא *alma*, what must you
do if you need dirt below? דגריר *Digarir*, you scrape it off
of where it is, you somehow remove it, sponge it off, scrape
it off, ומכסי ליה *u'michasei lei*, and then you put it some
other place where there'll be dirt below and you do your כיסוי
kisuy. *kisuy* in the new location. So הכא נמי *hacha nami*, if
that works by the knife, let it work here by the altar.
נגרריה *Nigrerei*, remove it from the altar, ונכסיה *v'nichseia*, and do covering.
So again how do you know that you do not have to
cover the blood of bird sacrifices? Now again it's interesting because you
know you would have expected until now every type of exception we
made is always been based on a verse. So you would have
assumed the first thing the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* would have moved to
is oh, I'll quote you a verse that tells you how you
don't have to do it by sacrifices. But it didn't. And we're
going to see in a minute, in a minute it will. But
we'll see the verse is not so easy how you get it
in the verse. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s actually trying to make
the argument here completely logically. That logically you don't do it by
sacrifices because you can't get the dirt below, based on רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira *Rebbe Zeira*'s teaching. And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said
well why not just move the blood, remove it, place it somewhere
else, and do the כיסוי kisuy. *kisuy*. Meaning what? So for the
first answer the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s actually going to reverse itself a
little bit. And actually for a minute suggest that you do כיסוי
kisuy by sacrifice, by the blood of sacrifices, which is amazing, which
suggests that every time there was a bird
sacrificed, part of the process in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would
be to remove the blood from the מזבח mizbeach and to do
כיסוי. kisuy We're going to in the end reject that, but for
a moment we're going to consider that maybe it actually did apply
to bird sacrifices.
I have to admit I'm surprised with this because, you know, if
I was back there, what I would have דרש darshanned is ושפך
את דמו וכיסהו בעפר. v'shafach es damo v'chisahu be'afar. It has to
be like right away afterwards.
And then, you know, now and then you're not allowed to do
all these... I understand, but we have other teachings that say that
you do. Now, by the way, those other teachings could have been
immediate. The only reason that they that we assume that they mean
removal in somewhere else is because we have to make it work
with רבי Rebbi זירא, who says there's dirt below. But it's the
same רבי Rabbi, זירא that's giving us a reason to say why
it won't work with sacrifices. But you're right, there is a re-reading
going on here based on רבי זירא. Okay, so let's see what
the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is. So the גמרא Gemara says אי בקדשי
מזבח הכי נמי. I b'kodshei mizbeach hachi nami. You know what? If
it's sacrifices, maybe you're right. Maybe we do cover the blood. We
remove it from the מזבח mizbeach and we cover the blood. הכא
במאי עסקינן. Hacha b'mai askinan. You know what? What do we mean
when we say it doesn't apply to sacrifices? בקדשי בדק הבית. B'kodshei
bedek habayis.
Not sacrifices, but we mean things that are sanctified that they belong
to the temple, temple ownership, but they are not sacrifices. So first
of all, that's a stretch because מוקדשים mukdashim clearly means sacrifices as
we know from the previous משנה Mishna, of אותו ואת בנו, Oso
V'es Beno, where it discussed מוקדשים mukdashim and gave the case of
שחיטה shechting them outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and שחיטה
shechting sacrifices outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But within this and
the גמרא Gemara will reject it, let's see why it says that
things that are sanctified for the temple treasury are any different. The
basic explanation, not spelled out but assumed is, is that we're going
back to this question about שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uya. That
if you שחט shachted something that is dedicated for the temple treasury,
so it can't be eaten. Right? I mean, it's holy, it can't
be eaten. If it was a sacrifice, if it was a חטאת,
chatas, you the כהנים kohanim would eat it. But a cow that
was sanctified for the temple treasury, the purpose is to be sold.
It can't be eaten. So therefore, because it can't be eaten, you
don't cover the blood. Now, we're going to see in tomorrow's דף
daf that although remember this question about שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina
re'uya was debated and the emphasis on in the previous פרק perek
was it still is the transgression of slaughtering the calf and the
mother and the calf on the same day even if it was
a שחיטה shechita that did not make the meat edible. Here by
אותו ואת בנו, Oso V'es Beno, the assumption is going to be
the opposite. Since the verse says כיסוי דם, Kisoy Dam, I'm sorry,
כיסוי kisuy הדם, because it says חיה או עוף אשר יאכל, chaya
o of asher yei'achel, that you slaughter a חיה chayah or bird
that will be eaten. So the assumption here is although actually the
תנאים Tannaim debate both cases, רבי is going to here rule in
favor that by כיסוי kisuy. הדם, the שחיטה shechita does have to
be one which the meat becomes edible because it says אשר יאכל.
asher yei'achel. So that's why it doesn't apply to קדשים. kodshim. If
we're not dealing with a bird sacrifice, but something that's owned by
the temple treasury, you שחט shacht it, it can't be eaten. And
therefore, that's why it doesn't apply.
So if only what I want to do is use its skin
for a pocketbook or whatever it is, you don't have to cover
the blood?
So that's an interesting question about whether it is that it can
in theory be eaten or that you intend to eat it. So
אשר יא... so we haven't gone that far. The biggest question about
שחיטה shechita שאינה ראויה is does it in theory make the meat
edible? Yes.
And then even a communal sacrifice given to the priest is considered
אשר יאכל. asher yei'achel.
Yeah, because a חטאת chatas the priest eats.
The כהנים kohanim eat the חטאת. chatas. The עולה olah is debatable.
We discussed whether an עולה olah is considered consumed by the altar.
But anyway, here we're saying that it's no longer קרבנות. korbanos. So
the גמרא Gemara says big deal וליפרקינהו וליכסנהו. v'liphrekinhu v'lichsinhu.
Why don't you just redeem it and then cover it and make
it edible? Now, the logic being that what do you do with
something that's donated to the temple treasury? You sell it and you
use the proceeds. Okay, you slaughtered it and now it's a mess
because you know, what are you... you know, what can you do
with a dead cow? But still, somebody's going to have some use
for it. So redeem it, sell it, and now maybe that it's
been sold and it's no longer קודש, kodesh, so now it's actually
good kosher meat. You know, although a question about what you do
actually with קדשים, kodshim, anyway, with things that you redeem. And now
it is edible, so now you should cover the blood. Now, by
the way, תוספות Tosafot asks the question, first of all, at the
moment that you שחט shacht. it, it wasn't... it wasn't fit to
be eaten. Right? And if you remember, there's a question you asked
me earlier. If you remember, that's the whole question. What happens if
something at the moment of שחיטה shechita wasn't fit to be eaten
and is only fit later? Is it... so by like אותו ואת
בנו, Oso V'es Beno, right, when you שחט shacht it and only
later you sprinkled the blood by a sacrifice, if at the moment
of שחיטה shechita it wasn't fit, does that count or not? So
first of all, question number one. You're only going to make it
fit later when you redeem it. But the bigger question תוספות Tosafos
says is you're still saying that קדשים kodshim are exempt. It's as
when it belongs to the temple, it's exempt. It only becomes obligated
once you redeem it and then it's no longer קדשים. kodshim. So
what's the question of the גמרא Gemara you should redeem it and
cover it, right? It would still... it would still be a case
that as קדשים kodshim it still remains exempt. So he doesn't really
answer that, but at least anyway, that is the גמרא'ס Gemara's question.
The גמרא Gemara says, I don't buy that that's the case of
the משנה, Mishna, because if that was the case of the משנה,
mishna we would not have said blanket you're exempt, because the normal
thing you would do with it anyway would be sell it, redeem
it, and then you would have to cover the blood. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, here's why you can't do it. והעמידו והעריכו,
veha'amido veha'ericho, you need to stand it up and evaluate its its
worth. Okay? Because the גמרא, Gemara the תורה Torah says that when
it, in certain types of cases, right, remember when the גמרא Gemara,
speaks about ערכין erchin at the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, it says
that if somebody sort of dedicates the value of a person or
an animal, whatever, it says you stand it, the person or the
animal before the כהן, kohen, והעמידו הכהן והעריכו לפני השם, veha'amido hacohen
veha'ericho lifnei Hashem, and estimates, determines its value. So the word והעמידו,
veha'amido, to stand it, means that that thing is can be stood
up and is alive. It's not like metaphorical, okay? It's not metaphorical
according to the הלכה. halacha. Okay? So therefore, since the animal is
dead and could not be stood up, you cannot redeem it. But
this is debated. וכמאן? ukeman? So who's this going like? Says the
גמרא. Gemara אי כרבי מאיר, ei k'Rabbi Meir, דאמר d'amar כל היו
בכלל העמדה והערכה, kol hayu b'chlal ha'amada veha'aracha, everything requires standing and
evaluating and redeeming, it needs to be alive, meaning everything, whether it
is a קרבן korban with a blemish or whether it is something
that is just dedicated to temple treasury. So if that's who you're
saying, then according to him you can't redeem it. So we're going
like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. One minute, האמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה שמה
שחיטה. ha'amar shechita she'eina re'uya shema shechita. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't
care if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is the author of our משנה
mishna and the problem is you can't redeem it, but רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says that even if the שחיטה shechita. does not make
it fit to be eaten, it still counts. So two different positions
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but if it's but they're both are
said by the same person. So on the one hand, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says it can't be redeemed, and then you use רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir to say that therefore this thing can't be eaten.
But it's the same רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says I don't
care if the meat can be eaten, it still counts as
שחיטה. shechita.
Okay. אי כרבי שמעון, ei k'Rabbi Shimon, if it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, דאמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה לאו שמה שחיטה, d'amar shechita she'eina re'uya
lav shema shechita,
that we're trying to say the משנה mishna works according to him
because since it can't be eaten, it doesn't count as שחיטה. shechita.
But האמר, ha'amar, the same רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says לא היו
בכלל העמדה והערכה, lo hayu b'chlal ha'amada veha'aracha, things that are owned
by the temple treasury do not have to be alive in order
to be redeemed. So you're trying to say, why do you not
apply to קדשים? kodshim? Because it's dead and you can't redeem it,
and therefore it doesn't count as שחיטה. shechita You don't have any
one person that says both things: that when it's dead it can't
be redeemed and that the fact that it can't be eaten is
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav
Yosef, רבי היא. Rabbi hi. You're right. It's not רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, it's not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's the author of the
משנה Mishnah is the, you know sort of the editor of all
the משניות, mishnayos, it's רבי, ונסיב לה אליבא דתנאי, venasiv leh aliba
d'tannai, and he switches vote. He sometimes he holds like רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, sometimes he holds like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. בשחיטה שאינה
ראויה, beshechita she'eina re'uya,
regarding the issue of a שחיטה shechita that is not does not
make the meat fit for consumption, סבר לה כרבי שמעון, savar leh
k'Rabbi Shimon, he holds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says at
least by covering the blood, it doesn't count. This is what I
said to you before, all the last whole פרק perek of אותו
ואת בנו, Oto V'et Beno, we said if the שחיטה shechita was
not fit, it still counts as שחיטה shechita and you still transgress.
But here, because the verse says אשר יאכל, asher ye'achel, here he
holds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and says that if the שחיטה
shechita does not make the meat fit for being eaten, then it
does not count. So here he holds that in the שחיטה shechita
has to effect the meat that it can be כשר meat, okay?
בענין, be'inyan, if it's קדשים, kodshim, why can't you do it? בהעמדה
והערכה beha'amada veha'aracha סבר לה כרבי מאיר, savar leh k'Rabbi Meir, because
regarding that issue, he holds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that even
something owned by the temple treasury, if it's not alive, if it
was alive and is now dead, cannot be redeemed. So that's answer
number one. What does it mean it doesn't apply to קדשים? kodshim?
Not it doesn't apply to sacrifices, it doesn't apply to things owned
by temple treasury, and the reason is because it will never be
able to be שחט and eaten. It won't be able to be
fit for being eaten after it was
שחט. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, and if you want I'll say כולה
רבי שמעון היא. kula Rabbi Shimon hi. Forget that whole discussion, it
all goes like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says that שחיטה שאינה
ראויה לאו שמה שחיטה, shechita she'eina re'uya lav shema shechita, okay? So
what's the issue here though, why not redeem it?
ושאני הכא דאמר קרא, v'shani hacha d'amar kra, the verse says ושפך
וכסה, veshafach vechisa, you shall spill the blood and cover it. מי
שאינו מחוסר אלא שפיכה וכסוי, mi she'eino mechusar ela sheficha vechisuy, sort
of like what Michael was saying before, something that the covering there's
nothing required to enable you to cover it other than the act
of covering. As soon as you שחט it, you can cover it.
There's nothing that is, you know, maybe it doesn't mean that you
have to do it a minute later, but there's nothing required to
take place between the two that will enable the covering. יצא זה,
yatza ze, which includes the case of something owned by the temple
treasury, שמחוסר שפיכה פדייה וכסוי. shemechusar sheficha pidyah vechisuy. Right? So even
though it's true that according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you could
redeem it, the fact that you need to redeem it, that it's
not going to be able to be considered to be a fit
שחיטה shechita, until you redeem it, the fact that it not is
not immediately a fit שחיטה, shechita therefore you are not חייב in
כיסוי, kisuy which actually, you know, fits into some discussions we had
before: what happens if at the moment of שחיטה shechita it wasn't
fit, and it only becomes fit later? So that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying, is still working within the sense that it's owned
by temple treasury. It's true in theory you could redeem it, but
at the moment of שחיטה it was not fit for being eaten,
and therefore you don't do כיסוי. kisuy. Now we are now we
are going to use this as a way to... Now we are
going to use this as a way to get back to the
simple sense of the משנה that קרבנות korbanos are also excluded, because
until now we're assuming that every time you bring a bird קרבן,
korban, you have to scrape the blood off the מזבח mizbeach. and
go bring it somewhere and do כיסוי.
kisuy Then you can't do that either. Okay. What?
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to say והשתא דאתית להכי, V'hashta d'asis l'hachi,
now that we came up with this idea to re-interpret the verse
in a way that says that it has to be potentially being
able to be done immediately afterwards, so אפילו תימא קדשי מזבח, Afilu
seima kodshei mizbeach, we can even say that קרבנות korbanos are excluded.
How do we exclude them? מי שאינו מחוסר אלא שפיכה וכיסוי, Mi
she'eino mechusar ela shefichah vechisuy, something that is only required spilling the
blood and covering it, יצא זה, Yatza zeh, which excludes this,
שמחוסר שפיכה גררה וכיסוי, Shemechusar shefichah grara vechisuy, that after the blood
is spilled, you're going to require to scrape it off of the
altar. So since something will need to be done, that's why they're
excluded. תוספות Tosafos asks how is it different than the blood on
the knife? Or תוספות Tosafot says because the blood on the knife
at least in theory, right, it was not, there was no need
for the blood to be on the knife. It wasn't necessary that
there's something, you know, that in the process it,
that something intervenes between the spilling and the blood. It could have
spilled off the knife and then you would have covered it there.
Whereas here by the blood that goes on the altar, the blood
has to hit the altar. So it necessarily has to go somewhere
before you do the כיסוי kisuy and you'll have to do another
step before the כיסוי becomes possible. So the whole explanation of why
it doesn't apply to sacrifices interestingly is not, is sort of based
on a verse, but also assumes רבי זירא's חידוש, chidush, which is
that you need עפר afar underneath. Without רבי זירא, the גמרא Gemara
has no explanation of why not do the כיסוי on the altar.
It does not have a verse that directly excludes sacrifices from כיסוי.
Okay, now we shift gears a little bit and ask, well, no
actually first we do a little more דרשות drashos and then we're
going to get into some nice little אגדתא. agadata. So let's first
have a little more דרשות drashos just to figure out how this
we know. So we've explained why it does not apply to sacrifices.
We have to now also speak about what else is excluded. The
bigger category that's excluded is בהמה, behema, something that's a domesticated animal
like a cow or a goat or a sheep. So let's take
a look at that. Okay, מר בר
רב אשי—I'm Mar bar Rav Ashi sorry, so first—so I jumped ahead.
One more verse. מר בר רב אשי אמר אמר קרא, Mar bar
Rav Ashi amar amar kra, so he quotes a direct verse to
explain why sacrifices are excluded. The verse says חיה או עוף, Chayah
o of, a חיה chayah, or a bird. מה חיה אינה קדושה,
Mah chayah einah kedoshah,
the same way it applies to a חיה, chayahs so חיה chayahs
can never become sacrifices, right, because they're never amongst the animals that
you bring sacrifices. אף עוף אינו קדוש, Af of eino kadosh,
so which bird does it apply to? Only birds that are like
חיה chayah that are not sacrifices. Okay, so this is a more
direct thing. It's not based on רבי זירא, it's not based on
the fact that you have to scrape it off and you need
another process, it's a straight exception. It's חיה chayah and עוף. of.
The same way חיה chayah is not sacrifices, birds are not sacrifices.
Now by the way, or birds that happen, that are—the same way
חיה chayah is never a sacrifice, talking about bird that isn't a
sacrifice. Now by the way, there's a certain logic to this because,
and I haven't totally figured this out, but you know, both חיה
chayah and עוף of are different in that you cover the blood
and you don't put the חלב chelev on the
altar. Now, you don't eat the חלב. chelev. Both of those things
are very relevant things in the world of sacrifices. What do you
do by a normal sacrifice? You put the blood on the altar
and you put the חלב chelev on the altar. So חיה chayah
and עוף of which are classically not—חיה chayah is never sacrifice and
עוף of certainly is not a classic sacrifice, these are things which
because they're out of the world of sacrifices, so you treat their
things, the blood and the חלב chelev differently. Although I have to
tell you, it seems like you go in opposite directions. I don't
get it. Meaning, the חלב chelev you say well, the חלב chelev
of a חיה chayah, is never put on an altar, so it's
not problematic, so therefore you can eat it. It's not sort of
potentially like something that would be headed to the altar. So if
that's true, where sort of saying it's not problematic because it's out
of the category, you would have assumed that you don't cover the
blood. The blood also is not powerful and problematic. You would say
anything you said cover the blood of a בהמה behema because that's
a blood that you would normally be putting on the altar.
The prohibition
to eat. The prohibition to eat. Yeah, I understand, but you're prohibiting
both bloods. I would assume the reason you cover the blood is
because there's like the danger that you might, you know, make turn
it, you know, use it in some sacrificial way out of the
Temple, that you might sort of, you know, attribute to it a
certain type of a power. So you would think that that would
more be by the blood of a בהמה behema than the blood
of a חיה, chayah right? Because it's the blood—no?
Maybe you're right, but this doesn't occur to me. I thought it
was more ceremonial ritual kind of thing.
Okay, so but why by a חיה chayah and not by a
בהמה? behema?
Well, a בהמה behema gets the, you know, the whole ritual of
the מזבח.
mizbeach But in cases—oh, you need to do—yes, but when you're not
bringing it on the—oh, you mean because within the category of בהמה,
behema, you do treat the blood with a type of respect that
when it's brought on the מזבח—ah, mizbeach. I see. So I was
sort of seeing it in the sort of לא יזבחו עוד לשעירים,
lo yizbechu od l'se'irim, you know, like the Torah is concerned, you
know, לא תאכלו על הדם, lo sochlu al hadam, the Torah's concerned
about how these things can be misused in pagan contexts. What you're
sort of saying is the blood is a life force and you're
treating it with respect. So the blood of a בהמה behemah you
treat with respect, at least in the cases when you bring it
as a sacrifice, חיה chayah and עוף of you have to show
another way of respecting the blood. That's good.
Well, but the way I say it, though, the way I say
it, it doesn't explain the difference that you would have expected the
reverse. Anyway, clearly there's something here connected to what is and is
not a sacrifice. Okay, so given that, what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is that look, birds are, you know, the reason you do
כיסוי by birds, it's similar to חיה chayah, because they're out of
the category of sacrifices. So when, you know, so therefore, I'm sorry,
so therefore if it is a bird that, you know, if it's
a bird that is a sacrifice, then you don't do כיסוי. You're
doing כיסוי here because it's like a חיה, chayah. because it's not
a sacrifice. Okay, so therefore, that's why it only, you only do
כיסוי when it is a non-sacrifice, like a
חיה. chayah מה חיה אינה קדוש אף עוף אינה קדוש. mah chayah
einah kadosh af of einah kadosh. So you only do it when
it's not a sacrifice. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, אם מה
חיה שאין במינו קדוש אף עוף שאין במינו קדוש, im mah chayah
she-ein be-mino kadosh af of she-ein be-mino kadosh, maybe it means like
this: the same way it applies to a חיה chayah because a
חיה chayah. is a species that never has sacrifices, so you cover
the blood of birds that their, the species of which never has
sacrifices. אף עוף שאין במינו קדוש. af of she-ein be-mino kadosh. הוציא
תור ובני יונה, hotzi tor u-vnei yonah, so exclude from the מצוה
mitzvah of covering the blood the turtledoves and the pigeons, שיש במינם
קדוש, she-yesh be-minam kadosh, that since those do come as
sacrifices, maybe even when they're not sacrifices you don't cover the blood.
Maybe the same way like by cows, the same way cows you
bring sacrifices, so therefore you never cover the blood, maybe I'll say
the same about turtledoves and pigeons since you bring sacrifices from them,
maybe you never cover the blood. So הוציא תור... hotzi tor... the
גמרא Gemara says לא כחיה. lo ke-chayah. No, we have to treat
it just like a חיה. chayah מה חיה לא חלקת בה, mah
chayah lo chalakta bah, the same way by the entire category of
חיות chayas you never, you make no distinctions and you always cover
the blood, אף עוף לא תחלק בו. af of lo tachlok bo.
So similar by birds, at least by the species of birds you
make no distinctions and you always cover the blood regardless of the
species. So if we're gonna make a distinction, it's not gonna be
species-based, it's gonna be whether it happens to be a sacrifice. And
if the bird happens to be a sacrifice, then already it's not
like a חיה chayah and then you don't cover the blood. So
this explanation number one is good because it doesn't require the whole
רבי זירא and the dirt below and speaking about the need for
another step. It's also very nice because I think it gets to
the heart of what makes the bird and the חיה chayah different
is that they are out of the category of sacrifices. And therefore,
when the bird is a sacrifice, then, then you don't cover the
blood. The reason you're covering these things is because they're not sacrifices.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara based on this and focusing on
the verse about חיה chayah, and עוף, of, switches from עוף of
and focuses on חיה, chayah and this is what I was saying
before, to the other exception about that בהמה behemah are excluded. So
אמר ליה יעקב מינאה לרבא. amar lei Yaakov Mina'ah l'Rava. יעקב Yaakov
the מינאה, Mina'ah, the heretic. מין Min sometimes also means Jewish Christian,
and very often it's used to talk about people that were giving
the rabbis a hard time in interpreting the verses. Like either they
were just doing it, you know, to be like troublemakers and to
try to mock the rabbis or so on.
You're saying it has to be a מין, min, they could just
be like a regular... what? I'm sorry, you're saying they could only
come as like a troublemaker or a מין?
min? No, I'm not saying somebody's a troublemaker or a מין. min.
I'm saying something characteristic... although it's a good... I'll keep that in
mind. Something characteristic of the מינין, minim, a characteristic of the מינין
minim in the גמרא Gemara is that, which also indicates some sense
that they were Jewish Christians, and that they were trying to, you
know, because early Christians, early Jewish Christians certainly were very into this
whole rabbinic mode of interpreting the verses, using the verses to try
to prove the Trinity, to try to prove this, I mean in
the Gospels, you know, Jesus, you know, who really seemed to be
a, you know, a Pharisee, you know, knowing the whole that whole
mode, you know, would interpret verses when his students were eating, you
know, were violating שבת Shabbos to eat the meat, to eat the
grain or other types of things. You know, there's interesting places where
he interprets the verses. So anyway, in a very sort of rabbinic
way. So anyway, that's a, that's a sort of thing that you
see sometimes about these מינין minim in the גמרא, Gemara that they're
debating the interpretation of verses. So let's take a look. So this
יעקב מינאה Yaakov Mina'ah said to רבא, Rava, קיימא לן, kaima lan,
we hold, חיה בכלל בהמה, chayah bichlal behemah,
that a חיה chayah is included in בהמה, behemah, לסימנים, lesimanin, when
it comes to the issue about the kosher characteristics, meaning, you know,
split hoof and chews the cud, the Torah says this is what
makes something a, this is for the בהמה behemah what is kosher,
but then it lists also wild animals. So you see that these
kosher סימנים simanin although they're said for a בהמה behemah apply to
a חיה chayah as well, right? Which is what we said in
the past, right? חיה chayah is included in בהמה, behemah, בהמה behemah
is included in חיה chayah unless, you know, otherwise. אימא נמי, eima
nami, so once you say it in one direction, say it in
the other direction. בהמה בכלל חיה לכיסוי, behemah bichlal chayah l'kisuy, that
בהמות behemas are included in
חיה chayah when it says cover the blood. It says if you
trap a חיה chayah or a bird, you know, and spill the
blood, cover it with, cover it with dirt. So maybe חיה chaya
means any animal, not just a wild animal. Now of course, the
implication there is that it does mean wild... and not domesticated because
it speaks about trapping them, okay, which is not normally what you
would say by בהמה. behema. But nevertheless he says if generally חיה
chaya can mean a generic, why do you know that it doesn't
mean a generic here? And maybe it should include even like a
cow and domesticated animals. So he answers אמר ליה, amar lei, so
it's interesting, like it's not like a big theological debate, but it's,
you know, he's trying to... but maybe he's still trying to just
do it as a way of challenging the whole, you know, rabbinic
interpretation in general. So אמר ליה amar lei he said back to
him, עליך אמר קרא, alecha amar kara, to you the verse says,
על הארץ תשפכנו כמים. al ha'aretz tishpechenu kamayim.
It says right by the blood, it says don't eat it, spill
it on the ground like water. מה מים לא בעו כיסוי אף
האי נמי לא בעו כיסוי. ma mayim lo bau kissui af hai
nami lo bau kissui.
The same way you don't have to cover water, you don't have
to cover blood. So there what says about, you know, there's the
verse in the beginning of Devarim where it says, you know, that
you don't have to bring your sacrifices... your animals to the Temple
once we get into Eretz Yisrael. If you want to eat meat,
you can eat it, you know, wherever you want in your cities,
slaughter it and let the blood spill like water. So he's saying
the point of let the blood spill like water... well what's the
simple sense of the verse? It actually is that you can eat
this animal outside and you don't have to worry that the blood
is not going on the altar, right? Although the whole idea, like
I said, the blood force and the life force, it goes on
the altar. No, if you can't bring it to the Temple, it's
not a sacrifice, don't worry about the blood. Don't eat it, but
just let it spill on the ground. So there it's saying let
it spill like water means you don't have to worry about it,
treat it like water, don't do anything, don't cover it. Okay? So
there it's talking about בהמה. behema. So that's where you see it.
מה מים לא בעו כיסוי אף האי נמי לא בעו כיסוי. ma
mayim lo bau kissui af hai nami lo bau kissui. So אלא
מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's true, יטבלו בו. yitbelu bo. If it's
really like water, why don't you go to the מקוה mikveh in
it? Now this becomes a little like almost mocking or like, you
know, the blood. So it's not exactly clear at this stage if
the גמרא Gemara, is taking over this questioning or if this is
still this יעקב מינא Yaakov Mina who's like just trying to undermine,
right? So he says, "Oh, if it's like water, why don't you
use a... why don't you make a... go into a מקוה mikveh
of blood?" So אמר קרא, amar kara, no, the verse says, אך
מעיין ובור מקוה מים יהיה טהור. ach mayan uvor mikve mayim yihyeh
tahor. A wellspring or a... or a pit, a gathering of water
will be pure. הני אין מידי אחריני לא. hani in, midei achrinei
lo. Only these things which are collections of water, other stuff no.
So ואימא, ve'eima, so nevertheless why don't you say הני למיעוטי למיעוטי
שאר משקין, hani lemiutei lemiutei shear mashkin, true, maybe it's excluding other
liquids דלא איקרו מים, delo ikru mayim, that never in the verse
are called water. אבל דם דאיקרי מים, aval dam de'ikri mayim, but
if you're taking it seriously that blood is called water, so even
if the verse says water, a מקוה mikveh is made out of
water, well blood is included in water. הכי נמי, hachi nami, let's
say that you still can use... go to a מקוה mikveh of
blood. So he says תרי מיעוטי כתיבי, trei miutei ketivi, no, there
are two limitations. By the way, if he is a Jewish Christian,
then you can think about the really sort of a subtext here
about going into the מקוה mikveh of blood, right? What purifies? Is
it the blood of Jesus or is it the water of the
מקוה? mikveh? You know? So although they also have the water of
baptism, but okay. But anyway, you just wonder if there's this whole
other subtext going on here. Like maybe he asked him the whole
question about חיה בהמה chaya behema
because he knew he was going to get this answer about the
water and the blood, which is where he wanted to end up,
go to the מקוה mikveh in blood, you know, which can be
a... you know, can obviously be a Christian subtext. So let's take
a look. So דאיקרי
מים הכי נמי, de'ikri mayim hachi nami,
maybe you can do that? תרי מיעוטי כתיבי, trei miutei ketivi, no,
there are two limitations. מעיין ומים ובור מים. maayan umayim uvor mayim.
That doesn't actually say a wellspring of water and a בור bor
of water, but he says the fact that it says מקוה מים,
mikve mayim, it says מעיין ובור מקוה מים, mayan uvor mikve mayim,
and מים mayim presumably describes all of those bodies of water. So
the extra uses of those other things, a מקוה mikveh and a
מים, mayim, etc., all of those are to say only water, not
blood. So ואימא, ve'eima, nevertheless say אידי ואידי למיעוטי שאר משקין, idi
ve'idi lemiutei shear mashkin, maybe they're both to exclude liquid other liquids
other than blood. But חד למיעוטי זוחלין וחד למיעוטי מכונסין. chad lemiutei
zochalin vechad lemiutei mechunasin. There are two types of way of מקוה.
mikveh. There's a standing collection of water, like rainwater, and then there's
a flowing water, naturally flowing water. So maybe it's excluding other liquids
from both of those examples, but it's still not excluding blood. You
only have two פסוקים, pesukim, they exclude from two types of מקוות,
mikvehs, but still not blood, other liquids. So he says תלתא מיעוטי
כתיבי, tlata miutei ketivi, it says three limitations. מעיין מים ובור מים
מקוה מים. maayan mayim uvor mayim mikve mayim. There are three words,
right? מעיין, maayan, מקוה, mikve, and בור. bor. So one of them
at least is there to exclude blood. So again, this was an
interesting, you know, the גמרא Gemara did have to address the direct
question of how do you know it means only חיה chayah. and
not בהמה. behema. Like by context, as I said, probably you could
look at the fact that it speaks about if you capture, but
the גמרא Gemara turns to a פסוק pasuk which really is talking
about the exact same issue and concern around covering the blood, right?
And this is also, you know, this whole idea that blood is
the life force, it goes on the מזבח. So it says no,
when you're not bringing it as a קרבן, korban, just let it
spill like water, which means don't worry about it. Don't eat it,
but don't worry about it. but let it just spill on the
ground. And that's how we know it doesn't apply to a בהמה,
behemah, but it still applies to a חיה. chayah Again, why exactly
a חיה's chayah, more problematic since it never goes on the altar,
you know, that's not exactly clear to me, but that actually, that
is what, you know, that is what the verse is saying. Maybe
again, maybe the thinking would be, you know, if we read it
that it was this more of this concern about sort of paganism,
that, okay, בהמות behemot we know we have to bring as sacrifices,
but let's use our חיות chayot for some different type of a
ritual, you know, for some more pagan ritual. So of course, if
that's what your intention is, the fact that the Torah says cover
it with blood isn't going to get in the way, but you
know, one thing leads to another. So anyway, it says because it's
a חיה, chayah the blood you have to cover, the בהמה, behemah,
תשפכנו כמים, tishpechenu kamayim, don't worry about it. What did you want
to say, Bobby? I was just wondering, I'm trying to figure out
with the girl, you know what, what it is, a water content
in blood? I mean, there's not... Oh, there's a very high water
content in blood. Is it not a blood content in water? Right,
so it's like we're saying almost the opposite, I don't know.
Well, no, I mean, it is true, by the way, that for
מקוה mikvah rule, sometimes things that are liquid and have a high
water content can count as a type of a water to add
to the מקוה mikvah to make it go up to the, to
get to the 40 סאה se'ah minimum, okay? But not here in
terms of being the basis of the מקוה. mikvah. Okay.
Yeah, but I understand, so we're saying that for חיה chayah. or
עוף, of, that עוף of no matter what, even if it wasn't
a species
that goes on the altar, right?
The only thing that's excluded is actually is a sacrifice, right? Because
they're linking it to the חיה. chayah That is right, exactly, that's
what's another.
Okay,
so now, now that we've done some nice פסוקים pesukim to get
to where we are about חיה chayah and עוף of and slaughtering
it, now the גמרא actually turns to a nice bit of אגדתא
Agadata which I think is a very interesting for people that are
conscientious consumers nowadays. So let's take a look. I'm not kidding, let's
take a look. Okay, so תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught,
אשר יצוד, Asher yatzud, if you trap a חיה chayah or an
עוף. of. אין לי אלא אשר יצוד, Ein li ela asher yatzud,
I only know that it applies to captured animals, right? ניצודים ועומדים
מאליהם? nitzodim ve'omdim me'aleihem? How do I know if it about חיה
chayah and עוף of that you're raising at home? Which by the
way, is not true by sending away the mother bird. שילוח הקן,
Shiluach hakan, sending away the mother bird does not apply for example
to chickens that you're raising on a chicken farm, because then you'd
have to every time you took the eggs you'd have to send
away the chicken, right? It only applies to things that you hunt
upon. כי יקרה קן ציפור לפניך. Ki yikare kan tzippor lefanecha. Yeah,
but here, it says you trap, but we say it's not limited
to trapping, it means even if you raise them. How do I
know that's true? So כגון אווזים ותרנגולים, kegon avazim vetarnegolim, like, you
know, ducks and chickens. So תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, ציד, tzayid, a
capturing, מכל מקום, mikol makom, regardless, even if they haven't been captured,
even if they were already pre-captured. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר אשר
יצוד? Im ken mah Talmud lomar asher yatzud? So why does it
say "if you capture"? לימדה תורה דרך ארץ, limdah Torah derech eretz,
the Torah's teaching you a proper way of behaving. שלא יאכל אדם
בשר אלא בהזמנה הזאת. shelo yochal adam basar ela behazmanah hazot. Don't
eat meat too regularly. Don't just eat meat too easily if you're
going... it only should be preceded with actually going out and capturing
the animal. And we're going to see in a minute this discussion
of what's the point here? So the גמרא's point is going to
be, seems pretty clear, that it is, you know, it is too
much of indulging in one's, you know, that it's not... that one
should strive for a life of moderation, it's too much indulging in
one's appetites to be eating meat all of the time. A, it's
a waste of money. B, it's too indulgent and so on. That's
the גמרא's concern. Another concern I should say, though, for some, you
know, people nowadays is that it's too... and this, you know, it
might be that the גמרא does touch on this, is that it's
too easy for us to eat meat, right? We go to the
supermarket, it's all pre-packaged, it's all, you know, clean and doesn't smell
and so on. We don't have to really encounter the sense of
what it means to take the animal's life, certainly as they did
in the past. So we're going to see here, I think there
is a little bit of a subtext of that, although more dominant,
the גמרא's concern is that of moderation and appetite, but the sense
of also a respect for, like, the life that you're taking. So
it says, don't just eat what... I don't know. So anyway, let's
just focus on this. Does that include chickens and stuff like that,
right? Because in those days, they didn't think of a chicken as
an animal the way they think of a... Well, I don't know,
it says חיה או עוף, chayah o of, it says עוף. of.
So... but the point is, is, so we'll take a look, because
obviously now, things that are more wild, you need to do it.
But what the גמרא is saying is even things that are domesticated,
your chickens and your cows or whatever, eat that, you know, don't
eat them, don't eat the meat without a certain amount of preparation,
like without a certain amount of, like, you know, don't eat it
too easily. "Oh, we'll just have some meat." You know, it has
a sense of like there has to be a conscious decision about
it. So let's read a little bit more and see where the
גמרא goes. Okay. So they're saying you still have to do it
if it's even if it's, you know, in your backyard. תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, yeah. כי ירחיב ה' אלקיך את גבולך. Ki yarchiv Hashem
Elokecha et gvulcha. So now we're going from חיה and עוף of
to בהמה behemah with the... The פסוקים pesukim we heard before, when
your, you know, when your, when you're expansive where you live, you're
not living close to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you can't bring
a קרבן, korban, so then it says, then you know, and you
want to eat meat because you desire to eat meat. Okay, eat
meat, don't bring it as a קרבן. korban.
So לימדה תורה דרך ארץ, limda Torah derech eretz, the Torah is
teaching you a proper way of behaving, שלא יאכל אדם בשר אלא
לתיאבון. shelo yochal adam basar ela leteiavon. Don't eat meat too regularly.
If you have a real desire, you know, oh, I haven't had
a good, you know, steak for
a long time, fine, you need to, you go ahead, you can
indulge in that desire every now and then, but you shouldn't have
it as a staple of your diet. יכול יקח. yachol yikach. Now,
I by the way, I meant to cut out but I didn't,
but there was recently an article, I mean not like it's a
חידוש, chiddush, but I used to like this columnist in the New
York Times, Mark Bittman, who wrote this thing in the food column
which was, what was it called? Something like the, I forget the
name of it, but it basically was always these great recipes that
you could do in less than an hour. Anyway, then I forget
what he called that column. Anyway, then he left and he joined
the op-ed pages of the New York Times. What was it? He
wrote a whole summary of the best of the paper. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, he has a couple of cookbooks, which I own. Anyway, but
then he became a columnist, he went
to the op-ed pages and he talked about like, you know, conscientious
eating and consumption and all those things.
And he talked about how biologically, you know, our, you know, when
people, our ancestors, you know, meat is very, very high in proteins
and so on, so and you know, when you had to go
out and hunt for it, you know, when you got one buffalo
or whatever it was, you didn't know the next time you were
going to have meat. So our body is preprogrammed to consume as
much as possible because you don't know the next time you're going
to be able to get that type of a rote of a
protein-rich diet. So he says the problem is, is that we no
longer hunt for buffalo and only get them once a, you know,
once every six months, and the fact obviously our body has this
natural built-in desire for meat, we eat it all the time, but
obviously it is not good most for our health and for the
larger, you know, world well-being of the world in terms of what's
needed to sustain that amount of meat production. So anyway, so that's
what the גמרא is saying, is if you have a real desire,
every now and then you eat it, but it should not be
a staple of your diet. יכול יקח מן השוק ויאכל. yachol yikach
min hashuk veyochal. Now, again, this is also where I said that
it's not, you know, it might not, it's part of on the
surface, it's really just about moderation and so on, but it could
also be about this issue of respect for encountering the life. Maybe
you can go ahead, you should just go ahead and when you
are hungry buy it from the marketplace, buy from some, you know,
go to your butcher, your local butcher, תלמוד לומר וזבחת מבקרך ומצאנך.
talmud lomar vezavachta mibekarcha umitzoncha. Don't, you have to, you know, you
have to own the slaughtering itself, you do the slaughtering, don't go
ahead and buy from somebody that's already, that's pre-slaughtered and taken care
of it for you. So again, on the surface I'd think the
dominant concern of the גמרא is that don't be too lazy, because
if you're lazy that'll increase your consumption. If you make it a
little bit harder, you know, and you really have to do it,
then it'll moderate your consumption.
But there could also be this issue of respect for
the animal life that is being taken. Let's read a little bit
more. It's like he's making it like אסור assur now. No, no,
no, it's not ideal. יכול יזבח כל בקרו ויאכל כל צאנו? yachol
yizbach kol bekaro veyochal kol tzono? Maybe again, you know, okay, fine,
but I'll just, I'll just treat all of my cattle and my
sheep as, you know, as just hamburgers waiting to be had. תלמוד
לומר מבקרך ולא כל בקרו, talmud lomar mibekarcha velo kol bekaro, from
your cattle and not all your cattle, מצאנך ולא כל צאנך, mitzoncha
velo kol tzoncha, from your sheep and not all your sheep. So
again, moderation. Do it when you really have an appetite, really, you
know, have some sort of process involved that it's not too easy,
you have to be the one to slaughter it, don't do it
for all of your animals. Moderation and responsibility, I guess responsible eating
here's the key. מכאן אמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, mikan amar Rabi
Elazar ben Azaryah, from here says Rabi Elazar ben Azaryah, מי שיש
לו מנה יקח לפסו או ללפסו ליטרא ירק. mi sheyesh lo maneh
yikach lefaso o lelifso litra yarak. If you have a מנה, maneh,
which is a certain sum of money, then, then you should only
be having vegetables. Take for your pot, like אלפס, ilpas, take for
your pot a liter or whatever, you know, a certain quantity of
vegetable. Don't go, don't go starting introducing meat into your diet if
that's all the money that you have. עשרה מנה, asara maneh, if
you have ten מנה, maneh, ten times as much, יקח לפסו ליטרא
דגים, yikach lefaso litra dagim, then you can take, then start having
fish in your diet. I was trying to think about this. I
think the per pound cost of fish to vegetables is about ten
to one. Right, vegetables depending on which vegetable you are, somewhere between
fifty cents and a dollar a pound, and fish is about ten
dollars a pound. So that works. So anyway, if you have ten
times as much money, then you can start having fish in your
diet. חמשים מנה, chamishim maneh, if you have fifty מנה, maneh, which
is five times the amount you were spending for fish, יקח לפסו
ליטרא בשר, yikach lefaso litra basar, then you can have meat in
your diet, then
take a measure of meat for your pot. So רש"י Rashi points
out that obviously for them meat was more expensive
than fish, but acknowledging that there are places in where it's the
reverse, and תוספות also spells out depending on where they were once
it was reversed. It is pretty amazing that it's a five to
one ratio. What? Fitness counts minimalist. Oh, there you go, right, a
minimalist, right. Okay, did you get that through your Wikipedia? Okay, anyway.
Okay, Google. מאה מנה, Me'ah Maneh, now if you have twice as
much, then ישפסו לו קדרה בכל יום, Yishapsu lo k'deira b'chol yom,
then you can have a pot of this every single day, which
means so it's actually interesting, right? Because here it sounds like if
you have the money for it, then actually it's not just it's
a question of not wasting money, which is what we would have
thought like maybe was not, you know, it was one thing about
moderate—one thing about sense, you know, sort of acknowledging the animal life,
which is probably more of a modern sensibility. But maybe that was
there. Certainly it was about not indulge—overly indulging your desires and your
appetite. But here the גמרא, this line seems to be shifting to
just a question of don't waste your money. You know? So, and
therefore if you have enough money, then you can have a pot
of meat every single day. I don't know, at least this one
has that concern as the more dominant one. But maybe the issue
is that, you know, thereby by spending, if you don't have a
lot of money on on meat, you may be denying food for
your something for your children, or whether it's clothing, or you know,
something important instead of your own stomach. Right, right, I understand. It
still is saying that your diet and sort of the more indulgent
parts of your diet, you know, should not be at the top
of your list of priorities, and money should
better be spent in other things.
But still, we weren't expecting this last line, which is, if you've
got tons of money, then go ahead, and you know, because it's
not, because then it's just a concern of prioritizing in terms of
things you're spending your money on. What's funny is though, didn't say
רבי אנטונינוס Rabbi Antoninus were very rich and still לא פסקו מעל
שולחנם לא צנון ולא חזרת, lo pasku me'al shulchanam lo tzonan v'lo
chazeret, which are vegetables? Right, that is true. That is true. But
that was that they had out of season vegetables. Okay. ואינך אימת,
V'einach aimat, other people, how frequently should they—wait, the מאה מנה Me'ah
Maneh is is vague, right? קדרה בכל יום? K'deira b'chol yom? Does
it mean קדרה K'deira of what? Right. But if it's just a
normal what, pot of vegetables or whatever, other people have to eat
pot—eat eat food every day as well. I I do realize that
it is a little—it switches from ליפסא, Lifsa, which is אילפיס, Ilfis,
which is one type of a pot, to a קדרה, K'deira, which
is another. But you know, רש''י Rashi at least assumes that it—you
could you could say, if you wanted to, that—yes—that it means if
you have a lot of money, so you know, eat gourmet, but
don't eat more meat necessarily. Oh, I see. Oh, that's interesting. So
eat a pot, like eat something, like eat a eat a nice
meal every day, but we're still limiting the amount of meat to
what we said before. That could be. That's nice. That's possible. Yeah,
I actually looked at רש''י Rashi again. רש''י Rashi isn't clear exactly
that this means a pot of meat. Okay, so now so thank
you, that is possible. So now the גמרא goes on, ואינך אימת,
V'einach aimat, and the other people who are not buy—eating meat in
their diet—I'm reading it now the way the מהרש''א Maharsha reads this
next line. רש''י Rashi a little different. Other people that we said
before don't have meat in their diet, when should they eat meat?
So מערב שבת לערב שבת, Me'erev Shabbat l'erev Shabbat, at least them,
once a week for שבת, Shabbat, then they should have meat. But
otherwise don't have, you know, don't certainly have like—certainly not red meat
in your diet seems to be the concern. Okay. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, צריכנא לחוש לדברי זקן. Tzrichinan lachush l'divrei zaken. So רב Rav
said we need to be concern ourselves with what the elder here
said, the elder being who was this? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi
Eleazar ben Azariah, you know, to consider that in when we're making
our diet—dietary decisions. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, אבא, Abba, אבא,
Abba, which was a name for רב, Rav, might have been his
proper name, רב Rav was like just an honorific, ממשפחת בריאים הוה.
mimishpachat bri'im havei. He comes from a family that's very healthy. And
therefore he can have a more austere diet. Interesting. If you're already
healthy, then you can have health—a more austere diet. אבל כגון אנו,
Aval k'gon anu, we, מי שיש לו פרוטה בתוך כיסו, mi she'yesh
lo prutah b'toch kiso, יריצנה לחנווני. yeritzena l'chanvani. If you just have
a dollar in your pocket, you can give give it to the
store person and therefore what? How's that different from the previous teaching?
So it might be again against the previous teaching about you having
to own the thing and go through the whole process and whatever,
and it could also be like you shouldn't—don't have to worry about
exactly follow—you know exactly this type of a diet. You go to
the store, you buy what you want. Okay? We we are not
able to live up to this sort of austere type of thing
we because, you know, we either desire more, or the belief that
some of these other things like the red meat or whatever was
necessary—more necessary for a healthy diet, and therefore we cannot limit ourselves
to like vegetables and fish. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, כגון
אנו, K'gon anu, like we, who presumably either have less money or
need even more rich food, לווין ואוכלין, lovin v'ochlin, even if we
don't have the money, we can borrow in order to buy. And
again, remember that one of the concerns of the גמרא was about
how much are you spending on your meal, right? Like if you
have this amount of money only buy this, this amount of— So
again, that's why the good סוגיא sugya ends, that discussion ends with
a clear concern not about indulgence per se and not about the
animal life, but about wasting money. So first we said here, don't
waste your money on beet, just deal with vegetables. And then it
says look, we need to eat these richer foods, or these higher
protein foods or whatever, so we are entitled to even borrow money
in order to have this in our diet. So it's an interesting
question about different attitudes and different perceptions about what was needed. Now,
how does this translate into normative הלכה? halakha? Very little. Now I
mean, but the problem really is not that it's not normative הלכה,
halakha, because when it says למדה תורה דרך ארץ, limdah Torah derekh
eretz, that's not meant to be legally binding. The question I would
more say is how much does this translate into sort of Jewish
eating ethos? And that's a point, a question. How much does this
ever get taught? I mean, sometimes you go to certain smorgs and
the meat, and it's very, it's really a little obscene. So, and
the question is, is that not that הלכתית halakhically wrong, but how
much do we have that's in general a problem, like how much
do we have a culture that we talk about Jewish values more
than just technical הלכתי halakhic considerations. So that is certainly something that
I would say is important. Okay, let's take a look. כבשים ללבושך.
Kevashim lilvushekha. Oh my God, we only have two minutes left. So
it says, the פסוק pasuk says כבשים ללבושך, kevashim lilvushekha, from your
sheep for your garments. מגז כבשים יהיה לבושך. Migaz kevashim yehiye levushekha.
From the shearing—so this is a פסוק pasuk in משלי Mishlei that
we're just translating each phrase—from the shearing of the sheep you should
make your garments, make them out of wool. Part of the point
here should be, don't waste your sheep on meat, like we were
saying before, use them for their other benefits. Also, as we're going
to see in a minute, don't have overly fancy garments. You can
have wool garments, nice garments, but don't go overly fancy like silk
garments. ומחיר שדה עתודים, U'mechir sadeh atudim, and the sale of the
field for flocks. לעולם ימכור אדם שדה ויקח עתודים ואל ימכור עתודים
ויקח שדה. Le'olam yimkor adam sadeh veyikach atudim v'al yimkor atudim veyikach
sadeh. A person should be prepared to sell his field and buy
flocks of sheep, and not the reverse. Exactly. Which is fascinating 'cause
there are other גמרות Gemaras that speak about the importance of holding
real estate as a very thing to be sort of, you need
land for your animals. Well, that's also true. Right. That's also true.
In this context we are talking about how many things are provided
for by the sheep. You get the milk, you get the wool,
and so on. ודי חלב עזים, V'dei chalav izim, sufficient milk of
goats. דיו לאדם שיתפרנס מחלב גדיים וטלאים שבתוך ביתו. Dayo l'adam sheyitparnes
michlav gedayim utlaim shebetoch beito. It's sufficient for you to be supported
off of the—or feed yourself off of the milk, milk and dairy
products I suppose, of the goats and the sheep in your house,
in your yard. Don't go ahead and start desiring meat and so
on. Again, the idea of get the wool of your sheep, get
the milk of the sheep, don't have to start—don't start slaughtering your
sheep for their meat. Which I think is really an important point.
Well, that's actually true, they did not really have a practice of
drinking milk. They made the sour cream, they made other types of
dishes that had some type of a sour milk in it. They
made cottage cheese, they had cheese and so on. Okay. ללחמך ללחם
ביתך, Lelachmekha l'lechem beitekha, from your bread, it should be the bread
of your house. So what's the דרשה drasha here? לחמך קודם ללחם
ביתך. Lachmekha kodem l'lechem beitekha. Interesting. Right? The general principle that you
have to take care of your own eating before others. Yes, yes,
yes. So first worry about your own food and then worry about
the rest of your house. We're going to counterbalance that in a
minute on the עמוד ב׳ amud bet when we ever get there.
וחיים לנערותיך, V'chayim l'naarotekha, and life to your youth, to your children
maybe, literally to your young girls. אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן:
Amar Mar Zutra bereh d'Rav Nachman: תן חיים לנערותיך. Ten chayim l'naarotekha.
Give life to your youth, your young children. מכאן למדה תורה דרך
ארץ שלא ילמד אדם את בנו. Mikan limdah Torah derekh eretz shelo
yilamed adam et beno. Interesting how he switched from girls to boys.
You should not teach your sons בשר ויין. basar v'yayin. Don't raise
them on indulgent eating and meat and wine. Okay, maybe also echoes
the whole idea of the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh whose
problem is the meat and the wine. So again, if you have,
or you eat, the most you get from your flock is you
get milk products and so on, and you're not having a lot
of meat and wine in your house, you are giving life to
your children 'cause you are raising them with the sense of moderation
and health and not indulgence. Let's just read one more line. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, says רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: הרוצה שיתעשר
יעסוק בבהמה דקה. Harotzeh sheyitasher yaasok bebehemah daka. If you want to
become rich, you should raise these small animals, meaning sheep and goats,
because they give you wool and they give you milk and they
provide a nice living. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מאי דכתיב,
mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse, ועשתרות צאנך, v'ashterot tzonekha, the
flocks of your sheep? Why are flocks called עשתרות? ashterot? שמעשירות את
בעליהן. Shemaashrot et baaleihen. They make their owners rich because again they
provide the wool and the milk. ואמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan,
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says—this is not really directly relevant—כי... ki...
I'd rather have a cup that has had witchcraft incantations said over
it, כסא דחרשין, kasei decharshin, כסא kasa excuse me, ולא כסא דפושרים
velo kasa deposhrin and not a cup of lukewarm water, which is
very bad for your health. חרשין charshin means witchcraft. Okay, so והני
מילי בכלי מתכות. vehanai mili bechli masachos. That if it was kept
in a metal vessel. This might actually have been germs and whatever
you get from like tetanus. Right. אבל בכלי חרס, aval bechli cheres,
if it was a pottery vessel, לית לן בה, lais lan bah,
we don't care. ובכלי מתכות נמי לא אמרן, uvichli masachos nami lo
amran, we only said it אלא דלא שדי ביה ציבי, ela delo
shadi bei tzivei, you didn't put in it certain types of herbs
or chips of wood. אבל שדי ביה ציבי, aval shadi bei tzivi,
if you put that in, לית לן בה, lais lan bah, that'll
counteract the negative lukewarm water in the metal vessel. וכי לא שדי
ביה ציבי נמי לא אמרן, vechi lo shadi bei tzivi nami lo
amran, and if you didn't put those things in, it won't be
a problem אלא דלא צץ, ela delo tzitz, if you didn't boil
it. אבל צץ, aval tzitz, if you boiled it, לית לן בה,
lais lan bah, which really does sound like it was some problem
about like tetanus or germs or something like that. Okay, I realize
we're late, but just give me one more minute because this last
thing just is the complement of what we said before about taking
care of your household. ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabi Yochanan, מי שהניח
לו אביו מעות, mi shehiniach lo aviv ma'os, if your father left
you a lot of money, and רש"י Rashi says if you inherit
a lot of money, you don't value it as much and you
waste it more easily if it was not wealth that you worked
for. הרוצה לאבדן, harotzeh le'abdan, so if you'd like to get rid
of it, here's a good advice: I have a ישיבה yeshiva you
might be impressed, no. ילבש כלי פשתן, yilbash kilei pishtan, wear like
not silk but linen, right, linen clothes which are very delicate and
very expensive. וישתמש בכלי זכוכית, veyishtamesh bichli zechuchis, use a lot of
glass, obviously at that time glass was very expensive and very fragile.
וישכור פועלים ואל ישב עמהם, veyiskor po'alim ve'al yeshev imahem, hire a
lot of workers and don't bother overseeing them, just trust them to
do the right thing. ילבש כלי פשתן, yilbash kilei pishtan, so what
are we talking about? בכתנא רומיתא, bechsina romisa, this Roman linen, which
is very expensive and very delicate. וישתמש בכלי זכוכית, veyishtamesh bichli zechuchis,
glass vessels, בזיגא חיוורתא, bezigga chivarta, white glass, again, very expensive and
delicate. וישכור פועלים ואל ישב עמהם, veyiskor po'alim ve'al yeshev imahem, hire
workers and don't oversee them, בתורי בדנפשיה פסידא הוא, besorei bidenafshei psida
hu, with oxen. So apparently if they can ruin the oxen and
they can just not only not do their job but even ruin,
like they'll, right, בתורי בדנפשיה פסידא הוא, besorei bidenafshei psida hu, they'll
even ruin the oxen. דרש רב אבירא, darash Rav Avira, זימנין אמרה
משמיה דרב אמי וזימנין אמרה משמיה דרב אסי, zimnin amrah mishmeih deRav
Ami vezimnin amrah mishmeih deRav Assi, sometimes he said this in the
name of רב אמי, Rav Ami, sometimes רב אסי. Rav Assi. מאי
דכתיב, mai dechsiv, what's meant by the verse, טוב איש חונן ומלוה,
tov ish chonein umalveh, good is the person that is gracious and
lends to the poor, יכלכל דבריו במשפט, yechalkel devarav bemishpat, who weighs
out his words in justice. לעולם יאכל אדם וישתה פחות ממה שיש
לו. le'olam yochal adam veyishteh pachus mima sheyesh lo. So this idea
of weighing, weighing your things and making sort of sound judgments how
you what you do. So a person should always eat less than
he is able to, which fits to the previous point, don't indulge
and prioritize your eating. וילבש ויתכסה במה שיש לו, veyilbash veyiscaseh bama
sheyesh lo, clothe yourself as is appropriate to what you can afford,
which is like wearing of the wool garment. Clothe yourself nicely. It's
about self-respect, about others respecting you. It's not like eating, which is
all just about physical indulgence. This is about respect for yourself and
the way the community respects you. And to counteract before what we
said first make sure you're fed before you feed your family, here
it says ויכבד אשתו ובניו יותר ממה שיש לו, veyichabeid ishto uvanav
yoser mima sheyesh lo, but you should actually the way you treat
your respect your wife and your children in terms of using of
your money to take care of their needs, maybe not food needs,
that was maybe although actual survival we have to say in the
end you come first, but everything else in terms of their other
types of needs they get provide for them more than is your
ability. שהן תלויין בו, shehein tluyin bo, because they depend on you,
so you have to be responsible for them and even do more
than you're able. והוא תלוי במי שאמר והיה העולם, vehu talui bemi
she'amar vehayah ha'olam, and you are dependent on God, so therefore for
your own needs show a little bit of humility or a little
bit of moderation because God ultimately is the provider and you want
to show you're being responsible, but for other people's needs, those you
have to give even extend yourself even further. Like רב ישראל סלנטר
Rav Yisroel Salanter once said in a somewhat analogous way, he said
יענעמס גשמיות איז דיינס רוחניות. yenems gashmiyus is dayns ruchniyus. No was
it? Yes, יענעמס גשמיות איז דיינס רוחניות. yenems gashmiyus is dayns ruchniyus.
The other person's physical needs are your spiritual needs.